The romance lasts from the late 18th century to the mid-19th century.
The current is strongest in Europe-
-When just finished a seven -year war and is in change.
The romance comes with its first emotional swallow sometime around 1780.
Then life was not fun, unless you were rich in an English castle.
We live in gray cottages, because we have not started painting them red yet.
Sanitarily it is lousy.
At this time, the enlightenment has been dominant in Europe for a hundred years.
Science has been worshiped and seen bright in the future.
Man and society will be better and better.
But then something happens that causes the ground to shake under the enlightenment-
-literally.
Half past ten in the morning of November 1, 1755-
-The lavish Lisbon by a strong earthquake.
Half an hour later, a several meter high tsunami pulls over Portugal.
It will be a huge disaster with great devastation and close to one hundred thousand dead.
The news is spread throughout the world and becomes a reminder of the power of nature.
Nature is central to romance, and as the cities grow-
-So writers and artists feel that they lose proximity to nature.
Therefore, the draw to nature becomes stronger.
Not just the relationship with nature changes.
When we move to the Stan-
-Communication is changed.
Safer
-And the need to keep in touch causes the letter writing to explode.
One person could write ten to fifteen letters a day.
There was not SMS or telephone-
-Or you kept in touch with friends and relatives by letter.
Then they began to release authentic letter collection-
-But also write letter novels, as fictional form.
One of the letter novels was the important work "The young Werther's suffering".
Johann Wolfgang von Goethe is German and 24 years old when he writes about Werther.
He participates with other young poets and students in a movement in Leipzig.
They call themselves "Sturm und Drang".
The words mean "storm and longing".
On that you hear about what it is about-
-And how important the strong emotions are.
The novel has a fairly simple action and is written in letter form.
The book becomes a bestseller.
Everyone should read it.
It is printed in three million copies.
Napoleon calls the "the best European book ever"-
-And boasts that he read it seven times.
It creates a subculture around Europe.
Young men dress in "Werther costume" with yellow vest and blue jacket-
-And dreaming of being unhappy as Werther.
Goethe took after a real event.
A young student, Karl Wilhelm Jerusalem-
-hade committed suicide of unhappy love.
Everyone realizes how dangerous this can be.
What if our young men read the book?
They are in love and want to be like Werther.
They want to be unfortunate in love as Werther.
Books are dangerous.
Some German Principality forbids “Werther” for health reasons
-To people not to shoot themselves.
There is no indication that people did.
They read and cried, and fell in love again.
But that the authorities believe this is symptomatic.
They realized what effect the romantic craze had.
Books got spread and an incredibly large impact.
One wondered how people would be affected by the fantasy world-
-and especially when the fantasy worlds did not come up with useful messages-
-If how one would be as a human being, without affirming the crazy and wild-
-When you do in "Werther".
Hans Christian Thulin has performed "Werther" as a monologue.
Håkan Hellström had a song, like this: "Young Werther's suffering" something-
-And everything that Håkan took in I thought was cool.
"'The young Werther's suffering' must be cruel as a monologue."
I knew I would never get Miss Lotte.
I hadn't read it, but thought of Sturm und Drang and hot feelings-
-Wigs and powder, so it must be fun!
We sat down and read the book ... and were disappointed.
We had almost thought that a book written in 1774 about love-
-Must be superdum and super fun.
But instead it was very real-
-Sorious and touching for real.
There is no measure.
It is important that romance-
-opposes the idea of moderation and tastefulness in literature.
To convey emotions, Goethe uses many exclamation points.
"The young Werther's suffering" contains 420
-What is 17.3 % of the book's total amount of punctuation.
Enlightenment's "Robinson Crusoe" has 2.8 % exclamation mark-
-And "Harry Potter and the Wise Stone" has 6.5 % exclamation marks.
If we read we see that "Werthers" first sentence-
-"What I'm glad I'm gone!"
ends with exclamation marks.
The second sentence of the book "Dear Friend, what is human hearted!"
Do it too.
When the writers of romance do not violate the rules-
-They look back and write novels about the past.
A well-known, romantic Swedish work that bubbles by nostalgia-
-As Viktor Rydberg's "Singoalla".
Just like "Werther" it's a tragic love story-
-But in a historical environment.
It is about the knight's son Erland and Singoalla who is Rome.
Singoalla!
The language of Singoalla is typical of romance.
"At the top of a hill in the forest grew a spruce, young and pain"-
-"But higher than all the surrounding trees."
"Her top appeared from the castle windows over the forest."
"When she signed up against a red evening sky, it was"-
-"As if it was seen out in the world and wanted the land of the palm trees."
We see the painting nature depictions and imagery-
-Where a spruce has emotion-
-and how dreams are used as a narrative element.
"Singoalla" takes place in the Middle Ages, which was considered töntig-
-and been called "the dark time".
The romantic should of course be counter -halls and like the Middle Ages.
The Romantic loves the Middle Ages.
They worship it!
What figures do we have?
King Artur!
Our old Vikings.
You pay tribute to the dark, the past and the irrational.
Romance causes our culture to make a streaming-
-From reason to emotion.
Nature, the stylistic grips and the craze for the past are important parts-
-But the center is the knowing man-
-which is more than reason and brain.
Love and longing are common themes-
-But what happens if the knowing man is exposed to something negative?
If she is exposed to something scary?
Well, we get one of the most popular literary genres ever: horror.
Again, nature plays an important role-
-But with something less dramatic than an earthquake: a bad summer.
At Lake Geneva in Switzerland, in the romantic Alps-
-You would spend some young friends spend the summer.
Mary, her future husband Percy and Lord Byron-
-Imagine walking and sailing ...
... but it was an unusually rainy and gloomy summer.
They needed to pass the time and Lord Byron came up with the idea-
-In the evenings, tell ghost stories.
Mary Shelley has written in her diary-
-That when it approached her turn, she got nervous.
She didn't come up with anything.
But one night she had a nightmare.
She saw a pale, young man cast life into a dead creature.
She was terrified by the dream.
From the dream came the foundation of Frankenstein's monster.
It is not the monster called Frankenstein, but the creator, Victor.
The novel is about his attempt to create a creature out of dead matter.
Give me life!
Under there is criticism of the enlightenment's idea of enchanting nature.
-As we struggle with and think about in the present.
When Victor Frankenstein built the creature and wanted to breathe life to the-
-So it is like when we develop artificial intelligence.
We want to create autonomous creatures-
-As in different ways interact with people, and help people.
I think we can draw lessons from Frankenstein.
What can happen to us if we do not handle the development-
-In a good and responsible way?
We must not rely on technology but need the human aspects.
Mary Shelley's "Frankenstein" re-released and has been filmed several times-
-As everything from horror movies to comedy.
The monster with screws in the throat-
-As even today one of our most iconic figures.
More female writers achieve success during romance.
-Not had the same education as men.
They were not schooled in Latin-
-And the classic rules that had applied in literature.
But now they got an opportunity when writing from within the subject.
But despite more women's names on the book riders during the romance-
-Is no golden age for equality.
During the sensible enlightenment, the women were able to elbow themselves ...
... but the female image presented in the romantic works around 1800
-Is an idealized picture of the woman as a innocence.
It is also something that has a clutch-
-To the literature that inspired, from the Middle Ages.
It recurs under romantic-
-This with the innocence and the unattainable woman as an ideal.
When romance was strongest, many got a new way to see the world.
Suddenly you had to place yourself and the emotions in the center.
Horror is still popular, especially as movie-
-And there is no lack of literature on emotions.
The romance came to stay.
The values of romance are still guiding us.
We are not as incredibly emotional in our style-
-When Sturm und Drang, with Goethe and Werther.